Guide to the Southgate-Jones Family Papers, 1760-2008 RL.01199
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southgate-Jones Family papers
1760-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Southgate-Jones family
RL.01199
22.4 Linear Feet
circa 13,456
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Southgate-Jones Family Papers (1760-2008) were donated to the Special Collections Department in 1970 by members of the Jones family. Some papers were transferred to the collection from the former Trinity College Papers in 1971.
Additions to this collection include: 2009-0020, 2010-0086 and 2011-0091.
Biographical Note
James Southgate
1832, July 26 Born, Edgefield, Va.
1849-1852 Attended the University of Virginia
1853 Became member of the Masonic Lodge in Norfolk, Va. Opened Norfolk Military Institute with brother
1857, Aug. 4 Married Delia Haywood Wynne
1861-1863 Served in the Confederate Army
1862-1867 President of Louisburg Female College in Louisburg, N.C.
1872 Moved to Hillsborough, N.C., and began Southgate Insurance Agency, later called J. Southgate and Son
1876 Moved to Durham, N.C. to expand insurance business
1876-1878 and 1886-1887 Appointed Worshipful Master for Durham Masonic Lodge No. 352
1914, Oct. 28 Died, Durham, N.C.
Mr. Southgate was a teacher and educational administrator who later opened the first insurance business in Durham. He was a member of the Royal Arch Masons and the Knights Templar. After his career at Louisburg Female College, he served as president of Olin College in Iredell County, N.C. Among his children were James Haywood Southgate (1859-1916) and Mattie Logan Southgate Jones (1864-1936).
Biographical/Historical note
James Heywood Southgate
1859, July 12 Born, Norfolk, Va.
1878 Became partner in J. Southgate and Son Insurance Company
1882, Dec. Married Kate Shephard Fuller (d. 1892)
1896 Elected presidential candidate on Prohibition ticket
1896-1916 Chairman of the Board of Trustees at Trinity College
1913-1914 President of National Association of Insurance Writers
1916, Feb. 22 Died, Durham, N.C.
Mr. Southgate attended the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill briefly before entering the insurance business. He played a principal role in J. Southgate and Son from the 1880s onward, serving as President until his death. He was the first in Durham to enter the banking business. Southgate was active in Democratic and Prohibition politics, and served as President, Director, or Trustee of a number of civic and professional groups including the Durham Chamber of Commerce, the Durham Land and Security Company, the North Carolina Peace Society, the Durham County Fair, the Citizens' National Bank, the YMCA, the Durham Public Library, and the Southern Conservatory of Music. He was Secretary of Durham Masonic Lodge No. 352 and a member of the Trinity Methodist Episcopal Church.
Biographical/Historical note
Thomas Decatur Jones
1852, Oct. 18 Born in Danville, Va.
1881 Moved to Durham, N.C.
1884, Oct. 21 Married Mattie Logan Southgate
1889, Oct. 30 Died
Mr. Jones was a dealer in fancy leaf tobacco, a business which he expanded profitably in Durham, N.C. He had two children, including a son, James Southgate Jones. He was a member of the Durham Tobacco Association and the Durham Chamber of Commerce.
Biographical/Historical note
Mattie Logan Southgate Jones
1864, Oct. 14 Born
1917 Helped plan women's parade for the North Carolina State Fair
1918 and 1920 Campaigned for the passage of the nineteenth amendment to the Constitution
1936 Died
Mrs. Jones attended Reverend Harris's College in Staunton, Va. Among the positions she held were President of the Durham Equal Suffrage League, President of the Durham Civic Association, and Chairman of the Fifth District of the Equal Suffrage Association of North Carolina. She was a member of the North Carolina Federation of Women's Clubs.
Biographical/Historical note
James Southgate
1888, July 23 Born
1905-1907 Attended Bingham School in Asheville, N.C.
1909 Opened the People's Bank in Chapel Hill, N.C.
1910 Became President of Southgate Jones and Company Real Estate
1917 Became manager of the Durham Morris Plan Company
1920, Feb. 7 Married Nancy Amorette Green
1920s-1930s President of the North Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham
Mr. Jones also attended Washington and Lee University in Lexington, Va. Before opening the People's Bank, he was employed at the First National Bank of Durham. He was a member of the Kappa Sigma fraternity, the Masonic and Pythian Lodges, and the Trinity Methodist Episcopal Church. He was a charter member and treasurer of the Durham Chamber of Commerce and President of the Durham YMCA.
Collection Overview
The Southgate-Jones family papers, 1794-1990s (bulk 1912-1933), are largely comprised of both business and personal correspondence, but also include printed material; photographs; genealogical information; business records in the form of volumes, reports, and minutes of meetings; clippings; and legal and financial papers. Several generations of Southgate and Jones family members are represented, including James Southgate, James H. Southgate, Mattie Logan Southgate Jones and James Southgate ("South") Jones. These individuals were involved in business, educational, political, civic, social and cultural activities in Durham and North Carolina during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Areas include insurance, real estate and tobacco businesses, banking, the administration of Trinity College, the women's suffrage movement, the Durham Civic Association, and Durham Masonic Lodge No. 352. The collection is useful for studying the history of Durham and North Carolina, the regional application of national policy toward farmers during the 1920s and 1930s, and the family history of prominent citizens.
A significant portion of the collection was generated by James Southgate Jones as President of the North Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham. This organization was one of twelve created by the Federal Farm Loan Act of 1916, to encourage farmers to purchase land with low interest, long term loans financed by the sale of stocks and bonds to investors. The bank was liquidated in 1942. The majority of correspondence dating before 1930 in the North Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham Series contains documents relating to the sale of farm land in North Carolina and, to a much lesser extent, Virginia; the financing of loans; and, after 1930, the increasingly harsh economic situation farmers faced as banks foreclosed on their loans. There is also discussion of foreclosure policies, relief programs, and the Hull-Wolcott Bill of 1933 in later correspondence. Included are communications with investment brokers in New York and Boston, property owners, real estate agents in North Carolina and elsewhere, prospective clients, banks in North Carolina and other states, and to a lesser extent the United States Treasury Department. There is also correspondence between James Southgate Jones, other officers of the bank and members of its Board of Directors. The series contains some financial reports from other land banks in Nebraska, Chicago, California, and Washington, D.C. Also included in the financial papers subseries are: lists of property owned, money loaned, farms for sale, farms purchased, and foreclosures; receipts for the sale of land and stock; balance sheets; and bank expenditures.
Other family business endeavors are documented in the Correspondence and Business Records Series. Both series contain information about the business endeavors of tobacco merchant T.D. Jones, including letters and notes from tobacco merchants throughout the Southeast who sold his products. Volumes in the Business Records Series record the financial affairs of J. Southgate and Son, an insurance agency begun by James Southgate and later headed by James H. Southgate; agencies affiliated with J. Southgate and Son; and Southgate Jones and Company Real Estate, headed by James Southgate Jones. Scattered Correspondence, 1890s- early 1910s, and a letterbook of James H. Southgate (1901-1906), relating to J. Southgate and Son, concern these businesses. As President of Southgate Jones and Company Real Estate, James Southgate Jones handled property in North Carolina, such as farmland and Durham homes and businesses as well as property in Virginia and New York. The bulk of the Correspondence between 1912 and 1914 deals with the promotion of North Carolina land to prospective buyers, especially in the North and West; and efforts of businessmen to make deals with Jones. These letters may be useful for examining the development of Durham between 1910 and 1920. There is limited correspondence regarding early land stock business unaffiliated with the North Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham.
Information on the civic and political activities of family members is located in the Correspondence, Printed Material, Writings and Speeches and Miscellaneous Series. Correspondence, particularly after 1916, was generated almost exclusively by Mattie Southgate Jones's involvement in the Durham Civic Association and a variety of women's clubs. The Miscellaneous Series contains materials relating to her involvement with the North Carolina State Fair, suffrage, and a Durham campaign for a waste disposal program. Correspondence about the suffrage campaign, 1918-1922, discusses soliciting names for petition drives, lobbying state senators, and political strategy and organization. Mrs. Jones was responsible for petition drives on the Trinity College campus. Other suffragist leaders with whom she frequently corresponded include Gertrude Weil, who served as Vice President and President of the North Carolina Equal Suffrage Association. A letterbook (1897-1902) kept by James Southgate concerns his involvement with the Masons, Elks and Templars. In addition to a small number of letters pertaining to his insurance business, the bulk are to other Lodge members and pertain to the Grand Chapter, the national organization and other business of Durham Masonic Lodge No. 352, including the sponsorship of an Orphan Asylum in Oxford, North Carolina. James H. Southgate's letterbook (1901-1906) contains a small amount of correspondence, 1903-1904, concerning his position as a Trustee of Trinity College, and includes discussion of the Bassett affair and the formation of Greensboro Women's College.
The extensive genealogical research of Mattie Southgate Jones is located in the Correspondence, Genealogy, Pictures and Miscellaneous Series. Additional information on family members can be found in the Clippings, Legal Papers and Financial Papers Series. The majority of letters written in the Correspondence Series between 1922 and 1934 consist of contacts made by relatives in North Carolina and elsewhere, in response to Mrs. Jones's queries. The largest amount of material relates to the Jeffreys, Jones, Southgate, and Wynne families. Photographs in the Pictures Series correspond to written information, and often unidentified loose photographs can be matched to labeled ones in albums.
The Correspondence Series contains a small amount of commentary, 1861-1863, on the Civil War, including letters from family members serving with the 1st North Carolina Cavalry Regiment. One letter includes an account by a civilian of the Union cavalry expedition from New Bern to Tarboro and Rocky Mount, North Carolina in July, 1863. The series also contains correspondence between family and friends. Included are a number of letters, 1906-1930, between James Southgate Jones ("South") and his uncle James H. Southgate, mother Mattie Southgate Jones, and brother Lyell Jones, written while he was away at school or traveling. Letters, 1909-1910, that South and Lyell wrote during a trip out West describe new surroundings, particularly New Mexico. There are also letters from South, Mattie, and other family members to Lyell from 1912-1913, during his extended illness and stay at the Winyah Sanatorium in Asheville, N.C. Other correspondents include James Southgate and Celestia Muse Southgate Simmons.
The collection also includes lantern slides, tintypes, daguerrotypes, and cartes-de-visites in the Picture Series. Subjects include family members and Durham businesses, streets and homes in the late nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries.
Additions to the collection have not been interfiled, and include business records, photographs, scrapbooks, a cookbook, and autobiographies of some family members. Please consult the detailed list below for more information.
The papers of James Southgate (1832-1914) form a separate collection in the Duke University Special Collections Department. Collections in the Duke University Archives related to the career of James Haywood Southgate include the William Preston Few Papers, the Trinity College Board of Trustee Papers, and the John Carlisle Kilgo Papers.
Real estate business -- North Carolina -- Durham; Women -- Suffrage -- North Carolina; New Mexico -- Description and travel; Tintypes (prints); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Durham (N.C.) -- Description and travel -- Views; Lantern slides; Cartes-de-visite; Insurance companies -- North Carolina -- Durham; Southgate Jones and Company Real Estate; Southgate family; North Carolina Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham; Jones, Thomas Decatur, 1852-1889; Standard Mutual Life Insurance Company; Southgate, James, 1832-1914; Southgate, James Haywood, 1859-1916; J. Southgate and Son.; Freemasons. Durham Lodge No. 352 (Durham, N.C.); Durham Equal Suffrage League; Durham Civic Association; Jones, Mattie Logan Southgate; Jones, James Southgate; Jones family; Jeffries family; Confederate States of America. Army. North Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 1st.; Weil, Gertrude; Wynne family
- Correspondence Series, 1794-1951 and undated (bulk 1912-1914).
  Scope and Contents note
  Business and personal letters, spanning several generations of Southgate and Jones family members. Most correspondence after 1930 is personal. Arranged chronologically. Letterbooks are arranged at the end of the loose correspondence.
  - 1794-1874(7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1875-1895(7 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1896-1909, Nov.(8 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1909, Dec.-1912, Apr.(5 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1912, May-1912, Oct.(6 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1912, Nov.-1913, May(6 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1913, June-1914, Apr.(6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1914, May-1922(5 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1923-1951(8 folders) (Box 9)
  - undated, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - 1897-1906(2 letterbooks) (Box 11)
- N.C. Joint Stock Land Bank of Durham Series, 1922-1942 and undated (bulk 1922-1933).
  Four subseries: Correspondence, Financial Papers, Minutes of Board Meetings, and Reports. Chiefly typed business correspondence, mostly to and from James Southgate Jones. Arranged chronogically within each subseries.
  - Correspondence
    - 1923-1928, Mar.(7 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1928, Apr.-Oct.(7 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1928, Nov.-1929, Apr.(6 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1929, May-Oct.(6 folders) (Box 15)
    - 1929, Nov.-1930, Aug.(6 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1930, Sept.-1931, July(6 folders) (Box 17)
    - 1931, Aug.-1932, Feb.(6 folders) (Box 18)
    - 1932, Mar.-Aug. 15(6 folders) (Box 19)
    - 1932, Aug. 16-Dec.(5 folders) (Box 20)
    - 1933-1943 and undated, 5 folders (Box 21)
  - Financial Papers
    - 1927-1942(2 folders) (Box 21)
    - undated (Box 22)
  - Minutes of Board Meetings
    - 1926-1933 (Box 22)
  - Reports
    - 1922-1941, undated, 2 folders (Box 22)
- Business Records Series, 1879-1917 and undated
  Chiefly volumes pertaining to family businesses, primarily J. Southgate and Son, and Southgate Jones and Company Real Estate. Volumes include policy registers, records of payments, ledgers, and letterbooks. Several pertain to the incorporation and transactions of the Standard Mutual Life Insurance Company, Inc., of which James H. Southgate was a founding member. A number of others are unlabeled, but appear to be related to J. Southgate and Son. Also includes a small amount of loose papers, including copies of individual insurance policies, financial statements, programs, pamphlets and notes.
  Loose papers and a small volume are arranged chronologically. Large volumes are arranged alphabetically by company and then chronologically. See Oversize Materials for large volumes.
  - 1858-1875, undated (Box 22)
- Legal Papers Series, 1760-1942 and undated
  Wills, deeds, indentures, stock certificates, military releases and other legal agreements pertaining to members of the Jeffries, Wynne, Person, Jones, and Southgate families. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1760-1942, undated (Box 22)
- Financial Papers Series, 1791-1943 and undated
  Chiefly receipts, but also includes bills, lists of assets, a secretary's report filed by James Southgate for the Durham Lodge and records of fraternity dues, financial statements, a volume for household expenses and an inventory. Represents the personal business endeavors of members of Jeffreys, Jones, Person, and Southgate family members in Virginia and North Carolina. Arranged chronologically. One volume is located with the Oversize Materials.
  - 1791-1943, undated, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Household Account Book, 1891-1892 (Box 23)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1883-1947 and undated
  Chiefly speeches given to local businesses and clubs, mostly by James Southgate and James Southgate Jones, and memorials; clippings about speeches; articles and drafts of articles about Durham, local families and prominent citizens, some of which were written by Southgate Jones and published as a series in the Durham Morning Herald in 1945; children's stories; poetry written by family members; and a draft of an autobiography written by James Southgate Jones. Contains fragments and some anonymous writings. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1883-1947, undated, 3 folders (Box 23)
- Genealogy Series, 1926 and undated
  Extensive research notes; lists of descendants, genealogical charts, and time lines which include birth, death and marriage dates; narratives of portions of family history; and correspondence, mostly between Mattie Southgate Jones and other family members and researchers. Also includes original letters from individuals, typed transcripts of ancestral letters, and texts of letters and other archival materials copied into notebooks; copies of family seals; texts of family wills; lists of property owned; clippings; and printed material including published genealogies and booklets. One volume of genealogical charts. Arranged alphabetically by family name.
  - Bennett family, undated (Box 24)
  - Hill family, undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Hunt family, undated (Box 24)
  - Jeffreys family, undated, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Jeffreys family, undated, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Jones family, undated, 5 folders (Box 25)
  - Muse family, undated (Box 25)
  - Napier family, undated (Box 25)
  - Norfleet family, undated (Box 26)
  - Southgate family, n.d, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Stokes family, undated (Box 26)
  - Swann family, undated (Box 26)
  - Thomas family, undated (Box 26)
  - Wynne family, undated, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous volume, 1926 (Box 27)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1822-1940 and undated
  Chiefly volumes kept by family members for personal and organizational records. Included are autograph books, address books, journals, a scrapbook, keepsake albums and fraternity rosters. Also included are clippings, printed material, correspondence, notes and loose organizational records. Divided into subject files and volumes. Volumes are arranged alphabetically by author if one is identified, and chronologically otherwise.
  - Subject Files
    - Dedication of Bennett Place Memorial, 1921-1923, undated (Box 27)
    - Durham Civic Association, 1911-1920, undated (Box 27)
    - Suffrage, 1917, undated (Box 27)
    - 1893-1953, undated (Box 27)
  - Volumes
    - Jones, James Southgate, 1907 (Box 27)
    - Jones, Mattie Southgate, 1882-1924 (Box 27)
    - Jones, T.D., 1877-1878 (Box 27)
    - Montgomery, Mary E., 1861-1869 and 1800s (Box 27)
    - Simmons, Celestia Muse Southgate, 1886 (Box 27)
    - Simmons, Celestia Muse Southgate, 1887-1895, undated (Box 28)
    - Southgate, James, 1852 (Box 28)
    - Southgate, Poly, 1818 (Box 28)
    - 1899-1922, undated, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - undated, 2 folders (Box 29)
- Clippings Series, 1888-1982 and undated
  Chiefly photocopies of articles, primarily from Durham newspapers, and a number of scrapbooks. Articles relate to Durham history, family members or other prominent citizens. Some scrapbooks contain poems, essays, stories and illustrations from contemporary newspapers. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1888-1982, undated (Box 29)
  - Scrapbooks, 1923-1927, undated (Box 29)
- Printed Material Series, 1822-1961 and undated
  Chiefly booklets, including catalogues and other publications relating to schools family members attended; and those produced for Mason, Templar and Elk conventions and special events. Also included are publications about businesses and Durham city government, programs for commencements, recitals, memorial services, banquets, church services, meetings of the Up-to-Date Club and other special events; and reprints of articles and speeches given at a variety of locations in North Carolina and elsewhere. Also includes periodicals, flyers, invitations and calling cards, most of which were generated from the religious, fraternal, civic, social, political and intellectual organizations with which family members were associated. Arranged alphabetically by organization, type of material, and subject, and then chronologically.
  - Durham, N.C., 1906-1954, undated (Box 30)
  - Durham Churches, 1908-1926, undated (Box 30)
  - Equal Suffrage, 1910-1920, undated, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Invitations, calling cards, etc., 1853-1921, undated, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Masons, Templars, Elks, 1860-1930, undated, 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Memorials, 1822-1924, undated (Box 31)
  - North Carolina League of Women Voters Newsletter, 1924-1929 (Box 32)
  - Organizations, 1895-1929, undated, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Programs, 1870s-1953, undated, 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Up-to-Date Club programs, 1896-1945 (Box 33)
  - Washington and Lee University, 1905-19152 folders) (Box 33)
  - Women's Clubs, 1916-1927,undated, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous, 1823-1899 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous, 1900-19615 folders) (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, 2 folders (Box 35)
- Pictures Series, 1805-1940 and undated (bulk undated).
  Chiefly photograph albums and loose photographs. Loose pictures are arranged alphabetically by last name of person when known and by subject. Albums are arranged chronologically if dated. Lantern slides are housed in a separate box following the loose pictures.
  - Photograph albums, 1936, undated (2 vols.) (Box 35)
  - Photograph albums, undated (2 vols.) (Box 36)
  - Photograph albums: (Box 37)
    - undated (2 vols.) (Box 37)
    - fragments, undated (see oversize folder) (Box 37)
  - Durham, N.C.: (Box 38)
    - 1883-1911, undated (Box 38)
    - T.D. Jones residence on Chapel Hill St., undated (Box 38)
    - Underpass construction on Chapel Hill St., undated (Box 38)
  - Jones:
    - Albert Lyell, undated (Box 38)
    - James Southgate [b. 1888], undated (Box 38)
    - Mattie Southgate [ 1864-1936] (Box 38)
    - Thomas Decatur [ 1852-1889], undated (Box 38)
  - Simmons, Celestia Muse Southgate, undated (Box 38)
  - Southgate:
    - Delia Haywood Wynne [ 1826-1888], undated (Box 38)
    - James [ 1832-1914], undated (Box 38)
    - James Haywood [ 1859-1916], undated (Box 38)
  - People, Identified, A-R, 1805-1900, undated (Box 38)
  - People, Identified, S-Z, 1885-1954, undated (Box 39)
  - People, Unidentified, 1890, undated (Box 39)
  - Places, Miscellaneous, 1915-1940, undated (Box 39)